<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Margarets in Westminster at the funeral of Mrs. Susanna Gray, daughter of Henry Gray, Esq., of Enfield in Staffordshire, who on the 29 of October 1654 began her eternal sabbath.</title>
            <author>Waring, Robert, 1614-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27055</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09626723</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09626723</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67616)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1345:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Margarets in Westminster at the funeral of Mrs. Susanna Gray, daughter of Henry Gray, Esq., of Enfield in Staffordshire, who on the 29 of October 1654 began her eternal sabbath.</title>
                  <author>Waring, Robert, 1614-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F.L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Consolation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43861:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43861:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON, PREACHED AT S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> MARGARETS IN WESTMINSTER: At the Funeral of M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> SUSANNA GRAY, Daughter of <hi>Henry Gray,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> of <hi>Enfield</hi> in <hi>Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire;</hi> who on the 29 of <hi>October</hi> 1654. began her Eternal Sabbath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come Lord Ieſus come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>And it was a custom in Iſrael that the daughters of Iſrael went yeerly to lament the daughter of Jeptha the Gileadite, four dayes in a year,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Judges 11.</hi> ult.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>F. L.</hi> 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43861:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43861:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:43861:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43861:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam 12.15, to 24. v. 22, 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he ſaid, while the Child was yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live I faſted and wept; For I ſaid, who can tell whether God will be gracious to me, that the Child may live? <hi>(23)</hi> But now he is dead, wherefore ſhould I faſt? can I bring him back again? I ſhall goe to him, but he ſhall not return to me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not only the wonder of of <hi>Davids</hi> Servants, but of all that read the Story, why <hi>David</hi> ſhould faſt and weep while the Child was yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, and dry up his tears upon the firſt news of the Childs death? why he ſhould mourn and afflict himſelf, while there was ſome hopes, with the fear of that death which he mourn'd not, when it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43861:4"/>happened? This is ſo contrary to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom and Manners of moſt men that ſeek the chiefeſt relief and eaſe of their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from their complaints and ſorrows, and indulge the ſad remembrance of their Loſſes as a kind of Reparation and Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy while they recover them, at leaſt in their memories, and find them repreſented in their tears, and therefore at the death of friends they invite others to bear a part with them in their grief and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Yet ſeeing <hi>David</hi> was a man after Gods own heart, and therefore his Temper and very complexion more refin'd and purified with holy allayes, and even, his paſſions are more to be imitated by us (for a good man is a living rule to others, his example the beſt Sermon, and moſt pleaſing direction to us, who are ever ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable ſinners, or Saints, and regard more what we ſee others doe, than what we ought to doe.) Let us Learn here from <hi>David,</hi> not from the funeral Preacher,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43861:4"/>how we are to behave our ſelves, what we are to doe in the ſickneſſe and death of friends (whether Children or other near Relations:)</p>
            <p>This one example leads us through all the Duties we owe to others in the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt caſes, this directs us: 1. How to behave our ſelves amidſt the confuſion of fears and hopes in the ſickneſſes of our friends. 1ſt, To ſeek to God before the Phiſician; to diſtill our Tears for Balm, and apply our Prayers for their firſt Cure; to lend them breath from our Petitions, from our ſobs and cryes, before the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death be paſſ'd, Who can tell whether God will have mercy on us, and not bereave us of ſo great content?</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. How to appeaſe and moderate our grief after the death of others, which we could not by our tears or prayers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. <hi>But now he is dead, wherefore ſhould I faſt? [ſhould I mourn or afflict my ſelf] Can I bring him back again?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3ly. How to return to our ſelves having
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43861:5"/>loſt our Friends, and from the death of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to prepare for our own. <hi>I ſhall goe to him, but he ſhall not return to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe 3 Conſiderations will beſt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Pattern in the moſt lively practical Lines for our imitation, and ſerve beſt to turn this ſtory into an uſefull moral.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            <p>How we are to behave our ſelves in the ſickneſſes and viſitations of others? Here good nature will joyn with piety to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force theſe duties.</p>
            <p>We are to conſider what ever preſent viſitations, as the effects and puniſhments of our ſins, as well as theirs who are viſited particularly indeed: This was manifeſt in this caſe of <hi>David,</hi> where the Child being truly conceived in the ſin of the Father, and born in the iniquity of the Mother, (in adultery) could have the ſhame and ſtain of his birth only blotted out by death, and covered by the Grave.</p>
            <p>But this may be a ſafe, uſefull, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per conſideration in the viſitation of any Friend, to look upon his diſeaſe as bred
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43861:5"/>from Gods anger againſt us, his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſins, as well as from his own diſtemper. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> How know'ſt thou whether God takes him from thee, as he did St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> friend, to free him from thy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions? who wert apter to delight in him as an aſſociate or brother in Iniquity, in Luxury, as that friend in <hi>Minutius (in erroribus ſocius, in amoribus conſcius)</hi> as a part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in ſins, a ready aſsiſtant in unlawfull pleaſures, and confident in wild exceſſes, endeared by mutual ſecrecy, and ſociety in vice; then as that friend charactered by the Pſalmiſt, a friend with whom thou mighteſt take ſweet counſell together, and goe up together to the houſe of the Lord, whence it is that God ſnatcheth him from thee, as <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> to prevent his infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and then his deſtruction by thy ſins; or elſe to free thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy immoderate Love and Carnal Affection; God removes the Object, and thus with Iealouſie courts thy affection, he ſuffers thee to enjoy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing over much, which ſhould ſhare in that Love and Devotion which thou ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43861:6"/>to God alone. Thus looking on chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (on friends) as greater ſtayes and contents of life, as ſo many Pins to faſten your Tabernacle on the earth; God loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens the Pins, to looſen your affections from the earth, and by degrees to bring you to a ſtricter dependance on him. Out of the ſence of this ſo affectionate deſign of our jealous God, did the noble Matron <hi>Melania</hi> entertain the death of a Husband and two Sons at once, with that pious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation: <hi>Expeditius tibi ſervitura ſum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne; quia me tanto onere liberaſti;</hi> Thou haſt, O my Lord, provided that I may henceforth ſerve thee more freely, having releaſed thy ſervant from ſo great incumbrances and diſtractions.</p>
            <p>In this regard <hi>David</hi> here uſed the moſt proper Cure of Gods anger, and his own carnal affections, faſting, weeping, and praying. Who can tell whether God will have mercy on me? forgive me my ſin and delinquency, for which the Child is ſentenc'd to death, that the Child may live.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43861:6"/>
            <p>This Remedy of Praying and Faſting for our own ſins in Another, is like the weapon-ſalve that doth ſo ſtrange and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret cures, being apply'd to the putrify'd matter, and the guilty weapon that made the wound, not to the patient,</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Conſideration, that ſickneſſes, being but the Attachments and approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of death, are (as death is ſaid to be) the wages of ſin, ſets us on our firſt work, To remove the Cauſe, our ſins, before we may hope to take away the Effect, the diſeaſe of our friend. This Order the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Canons ſeem'd to point at, which enjoyned the ſick to ſend for his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, before his Phyſician. Think then thy friends conſumption proceeds from thy languiſhing towards God, from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of holy heat and zeal in thee. Think his Feaver but a juſt judgement on thy impure flames of Luſt, or Envy, or Revenge, or thy immoderate affection towards him; his Lameneſſe upbraids thy halting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and the world; his Stone the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43861:7"/>Symptome of the hardneſſe of thy heart; his bad ſpleen argues thy rotten malice, and what ever corruptions anſwering ſtill ſome more corrupt deſires of thy Soul, ſo wilt thou find as great neceſsity to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and purge thy Soul, as the others bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After the Cauſe is removed, by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing away with thy tears thine own or thy friends ſtams, then mayſt thou ſafely, orderly (and as the Phyſicians preſcribe <hi>ſecundum artem</hi>) proceed to remove the Effect; to uſe all the means God allows for recovery; for to this end (ſaith the wiſe man) God created the Phiſician as well as the herbs of the field, for the time of need: Only remember that you firſt beg the life of God, before you ſeek it from the Phiſician. 'Twas <hi>Aſahs</hi> fault, not that he ſought the Phiſician, but that he did not ſeek the Lord; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12. only as you uſe the means, ſo truſt not in them, but in Gods bleſſing, and believe they have no farther operation, or vertue, than
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43861:7"/>while they are joyn'd with your Prayers. <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> Recovery St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſcribes to Gods mercy on him, and on the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but his mercy awakened by prayers, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.26, 27. his own preſervation from the ſentence of death paſſ'd againſt him at <hi>Epheſus</hi> to combate with wild beaſts [1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 32. which was drawn upon him by more Salvage Beaſts; <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his Silver Smithes, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.24] he imputes to the Prayers of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10, 11. Who knowes whether our letting our hands fall from prayer hath not cauſ'd death to prevail over the perſon we now mourn for?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Duty or enquiry. How we are to moderate our grief in the death of near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which by theſe degrees will be diſcovered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some affections, ſome natural paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are not to be denied; God doth not, like the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> load his Children with ſtripes, and require that hardineſſe in them, that they ſhould return no ſigns
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43861:8"/>of griefs nor groans at all. 'Tis no ſtoical Apathy, no ſenſeleſſe ſtupidity God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, but only patience under his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements; for if we did not feel the blow, how ſhould we look up to the hand that ſmites us? How ſhould afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lead us to godly ſorrow, but by that ſenſible ſorrow which is according to the world? that which is natural is firſt, and then that which is ſpiritual. Even world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſadneſſe, and melancholly is a good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Devotion, and a fair degree to an humble temper. We find our Saviour weeping over <hi>Lazarus</hi> Grave, inſomuch as the people could inferr thence, <hi>See how much he loved him.</hi> John 11.35, 36. I know no Divinity (but that which the Sword and the Spirit, unlike that which came in the ſhape of a Dove, hath framed in this latter age) that excludes humanity, but delights always to plant it ſelf in ſoft breaſts, and either makes or finds good nature. I find in the Catalogue, and Spawne of higheſt Crimes (which the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43861:8"/>dreggs of theſe laſt times ſhould bring forth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, want of natural affection, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 33. and that joyn'd with Haters of God, Truce breakers, Falſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, unthankfull, curſed Speakers, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſhew of godlineſſe, and denying the power thereof (<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30.) And the Apoſtle argues it ſtrongly; <hi>How can he love God whom he hath not ſeen, who loves not his brother whom he hath ſeen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, tis not only not unlawfull, but a duty to mourn with thoſe that mourn, if you will receive the Apoſtles Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. It is in the Scripture no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as an extream judgement and curſe on the wicked, <hi>Job</hi> 27.15. (<hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.64.) his Widows ſhall not weep, as either wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting leaſure from other ſorrows, or liberty from their cruel enemies, or oppreſſed with Gods ſore diſpleaſure, ſo far as to yeeld and acknowledge the juſt curſe with ſilence, <hi>Jer</hi> 16.5.7. or elſe, having ſpent their tears and grief, and dryed up the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of ſorrow, their very heart, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.16,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43861:9"/>17.22.23. that the heavieſt judgement you ſhall not mourn nor weep, but ſhall pine away in your iniquity, and mourn one towards another, for one to comfort ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c. Tears are the firſt office we do for our ſelves, and the laſt for others.</p>
            <p>They may not pleaſe themſelves, that can with dryeſt eyes behold the ſickneſſes, the loſſes, the Funerals of Friends, as who had attain'd a greater meaſure of Religion or Diſcretion, or the Spirit, or who had ſubdued their deſires to a perfecter Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and ſubmiſsion to Gods will. Let them queſtion themſelves whether this Apathy, this ſtoutneſs, proceeds not from a ſpirit void of ſenſe and natural affection, and not from an humble Reſignation to the Providence and pleaſure of God; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this calm ariſe not alike to that of the dead Sea, from a curſe?</p>
            <p n="2">2. On the other ſide, Though Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forbids not mourning, yet it forbids us to mourn as thoſe that have no hopes; Though it excludes not all grief, yet it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43861:9"/>our grief, and teacheth us to turne our ſadneſs to an holy ſorrow, our melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly to devotion, and convert our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents to repentance. Religion other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will require us to weep our Carnal Tears over again, when they flow either from immoderate or mere worldly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Hence then we are to enquire,</p>
            <p n="3">3. How farr we are to mourn? For what, and how we are to grieve? and and that either in regard of the <hi>Object,</hi> or <hi>Meaſure of our grief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of the meaſure of our grief, we are ſo far to mourn, as we joyn prayers with our tears; ſo far, (which is the true meaſure of all our paſsions, by which we may diſcern when they are immoderate) as not to indulge fruitleſs tears and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, inſtead of real duties. When our paſsions hinder not the free uſe of reaſon and Religion, and take not up the place of other Services; when they cauſe us not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43861:10"/>to omit the Evening Sacrifice, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did upon grief for the death of his two Sons, <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, Lev.</hi> 10. <hi>ult.</hi> which yet <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſaid to be content with, and God to permit, not that he indulgeth more the extremities of this paſsion, (which moſt baniſheth the ſenſe of Humanity or Piety) but in regard of ſome holy Reflection in this his greif, that included ſome ſorrow for the ſcandal and breach of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. This may be ſome cauſe why God would not permit his Prieſts that naturall Affection, to mourn for any friends, but their neareſt kin, <hi>Lev.</hi> 21.2. Leſt it ſhould make them leſſe holy, God would have them leſs humane then others. He would have them eſteem no relation ſo near to them, as that of God, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; He ſuffers them not to grieve for the loſs of any thing, while they may, in ſo near a diſtance, enjoy God; the reaſon is alleaged <hi>verſe</hi> 6. In them it is interpreted Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, what in others were but a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable affection, and ſign of a good nature;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43861:10"/>ſeeing ſorrow indulg'd, muſt needs bring with it ſome diſtraction in Religion. The Heavineſs of heart for Chriſts departure, caus'd the Diſciples to ſleep, when they ſhould have watched and pray'd. St. <hi>Gregory</hi> breaks off his Comment on <hi>Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> to write Epitaphs on his Son; as <hi>Aaron</hi> omits the evening ſacrifice, or a great part of the Ceremonie, at his Sons death.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In regard of the object; we are to mourn for ſins firſt, and then for afflictions, ſickneſſes, deaths, as the Effects and Conſequents of ſin. So that death, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evils, are the improper and ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry objects of ſorrow, Sin the onely proper object of grief, and juſt cauſe of tears;</p>
            <p>Becauſe, 1ſt, Sin is the only evil, <hi>John</hi> 17.15. being the cauſe of all other evils: and without which, miſeries themſelves are not miſerable, but are turned to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent to Exerciſes of their graces, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of redoubled Rewards and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sorrow in other evils; ſave in ſins
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43861:11"/>only, is uſeleſs, and brings no proper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but adds more diſquiet to our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Our tears naturally fall upon our breaſts, as it were to waſh the ſtains of that part; and are not to be waſted over graves, that may ſave ſouls. Our tears ('twas the complaint of St. <hi>Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtome</hi>) are moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd by us; wee laviſh and ſpend them where they are not availeable on outward evils, or over the dead. We ſeldom (ſaith he) weep in the right place.</p>
            <p>But, as ſins firſt deſerve our ſorrow, ſo affliction and miſery, the conſequents of ſin, more ſenſibly provoke our griefs, and are indeed the juſt, but ſecondary cauſe and objects of Sorrow. Whence Sickneſſes and Deaths are to be conſidered &amp; look'd on as the wages (nothing ſurer than the Hirelings wages) the effects and conſequents of Sin.</p>
            <p>For firſt, ſo Sin and Affliction in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture are both repreſented under the name of Death. <hi>Open my eyes, O Lord, that I ſleep not in death;</hi> that is, in Sin that leads unto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43861:11"/>Death, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Pray unto the Lord to take away this death only, Exod.</hi> 10.17. that is, the plague of Vermin, that did not ſo much threaten to deſtroy, as to diſquiet <hi>Pharoabs</hi> life; In the Prophet, (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.) ſword without, and death within, is threatned, when Famine, Plague, and other meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of death are denounced, whereupon the wiſe man concludes ſafely, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.38. <hi>He that loves ſin, loves death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To look on Affliction otherwiſe, as not ſent by providence, either to puniſh or to diſcipline us: as the Fiery Tryal, either to refine and purge, to better us, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume us: as the Wind, either to fanne or to ſcatter us utterly; is to look on them no otherwiſe than the Heathen, as Chances, and the caſual events of the Fates. Thus to bear them as things of courſe, without any thoughts of Sin, is to ſay that afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riſeth out of the duſt, or (what is a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy God leſs endureth) That God willingly grieveth the children of men, (<hi>Jupiter non nocet, niſi ut proſit,</hi> Sen.)</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43861:12"/>
            <p>From this conſideration, (that Death and all other evils, are the effects and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents of Sin) will follow theſe father Inferences.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Againſt ſecurity in health or youth, that as Death came into the world by Sin, ſo it came over all the world, in that all have ſinned: that we may not wonder when we find Children conceived in Sin ſhould have death bequeathed to them, before they are well entred into life. Whence they which are not marks large enough for any of Deaths darts, for any wound, are yet wounded ſo often by it, and find their grave in the womb, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Child that is not grown to <hi>Davids</hi> ſpan, is yet old enough to die. No ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in any place or ſtate of life, while we car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry about us, not a body only, but a ſoule temper'd with contrary and corrupt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and a body of ſin and death, as well as of fleſh. We may conclude with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.10. <hi>The body is dead through ſin.</hi> VVhat wonder if ſo many are cut off
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43861:12"/>in the flower of their ſtrength, e're they well know how to live, and leſſe how to die. 'Tis the ſinner, not the ſick or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged perſon, dies. Paradice alone had the tree of Life in it; when <hi>Adam</hi> was caſt out of that, into this our Farth, he brought nothing but Death, and the Emblemes of Mortality: See him no ſooner faln, than caſt out of Paradice, a flaming ſword, and a deſtroying Angel driving him from the Tree of Life: the skins of Beaſts, that is, Mortality it ſelf ſerving to cover him; and at laſt he condemn'd to dig continually the earth, and to prepare his own Grave; His poſterity ever ſince feeding their Luxury, and ſuſtaining their life with the death of birds and beaſts <hi>(mortibus veſcimur)</hi> doth not he ſeem to have planted in this our earth the tree of Death? whereon all the fruits periſh, e'r they come to maturity, ſome in the bud, others in the growth. VVe paſſe through ſo many deaths to Eternal life: from the womb of the mother, of the world, of the earth, to heaven. In the midſt of life we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43861:13"/>are in death, and like ſentenc'd perſons, under a reprieve, however we are permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to live, yet to enjoy no certaintie of life, as not knowing when we may be called forth to execution. VVhile we walk upon earth, we alwayes tread over our graves, and know not whether our next ſtep may bring us into it. For our bed is made in the dark, and our graves lie ready open for us, but as pits covered with ſnow.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Againſt impatience, or Immoderat ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. If ſin brings forth death, we are to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider death as an evil, not ſo much inflicted by God, as drawn upon our ſelves by our own deſerts, &amp; as it were our own choice; and therefore with more patience to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> c. 1.13, 16. God made not death (<hi>adeo non est creatione, ſed ordinatione aut ultione in poenam peccati,</hi> he fram'd it not, he meant it not for a creature, but ordain'd it for a puniſhment of his diſobedient crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) for then ſhould the great work-man have deſtroy'd his own works, which yet he allow'd to be good; the Creator
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43861:13"/>ſhould have been the <hi>Abbaddon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Confounder of his own creature; but death was the creature of Mans Invention, and as his own brood, makes way for its birth, like the Viper; by eating through the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails of the Parent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Againſt fear of death as well as ſorrow, that as other Afflictions, ſo death in its ſelf is not ſimply evil, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſimply to be fear'd or mourn'd, but in reference to ſin, the ſting of death is ſin. Sin alone makes death deadly, and miſeries miſerable. Death, like thoſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. which take their colours from the place to which they cleave (as the <hi>Polypus</hi> and <hi>Camaeleon</hi>) becomes good or evill, as the perſons are to whom it happens: It is the voice from Heaven, could our dull earth be perſwaded to hear it, that they are bleſſed who die in the Lord, What is it then we mourn for? either our friends loſſe? who is more bleſsed by dying in the Lord (<hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13.) who hath exchang'd the company of helpleſs friends, for the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43861:14"/>of Angels, the Valley of Tears for the Regions of Joy; and (in a word) Earth for Heaven: or do we mourn (which is the truth if we would put off out mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veil) our own loſs of a friend? a loſs of a content, of an Inſtrument of Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which ſtill remains the ſame, and retains the ſame power and goodneſs, to ſupply as great contents as it hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</p>
            <p>Whence will follow the laſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this point of moderating our grief.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Having ordered aright out ſorrows, the better to moderate them, we are to learn from <hi>David</hi> how to dry up our Tears, How to comfort our ſelves in the death of friends?</p>
            <p n="1">1. From their happy Fate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the hope of a better life, whereof we receive any ſigns or aſſurances at their death. This was <hi>Davids</hi> main comfort here, I ſhall goe to him, &amp;c. the Child had got the Goal before him. <hi>David</hi> that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43861:14"/>wept ſo impatiently for <hi>Abſolon,</hi> wept not at all for this his dear infant, begot indeed in ſin, but dying in innocence <hi>(David par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricidam Abſolonem) mortuum flevit, non Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, fletur ſceleratus, non fletur Dilectus,</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros de f. Reſ c. 4.) Now the hopes of ſalvation are the ſureſt and infallible in baptized children. They are undoubtedly ſav'd ſaith our Church. And the Scripture aſſures by infinite arguments of it, that to little children belongeth the Kingdom of Heaven. For by Baptiſm having put on Chriſt, having paſt the laver of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, having drown'd the old man in Chriſts blood and death, and raiſ'd the new man, waſh'd and cleanſ'd out of water, as it were to preſent Reſurrection (ſeeing God ſaves by water the new world, as he deſtroyed the old, and that none could periſh in the Ark) whereof Baptiſm is the Antitype, (ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi>) how can we doubt but that Chriſt receives them into his Arms in Heaven, as well as on Earth? and that they muſt needs be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43861:15"/>admitted into Paradice, who bring that innocence thither, which <hi>Adam</hi> loſt? Next to Children, our Hopes are moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of thoſe, who have come neareſt thoſe little ones, and paſſ'd their days in a Child-like Innocence and ſimplicity; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no opinions, no affections of their own; but what their Heavenly Father di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects. Theſe we part with upon the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt Terms,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Ut praemiſſos non amiſſos)</hi> as only gone before,<note place="margin">Profectio eſt quam putas mortem. cur mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratè feras abiiſſe, quent mox ſubſequeris [Tert. de pat.] Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis vitae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſusnec illi multum videtur e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripuiſſe, nec tibi diſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſe. [Amb.] Reſ. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> not taken away from us, as one abſent and retired to a warmer Clime and happier Region, not loſt, not dead; And why doſt thou ſo impatiently bear his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, whom thou art ere long to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? For he whom thou perſecuteſt thus with ſad thoughts, is but divided from thee by a ſhort <hi>Iſthmas</hi> (the breadth of the Grave) a narrow ſcantling and ſpace of Time, ſome fews dayes or moneths, or at moſt ſome few years, which are either taken from him, or reſerv'd to thee. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive then the bleſſed Spirits departed in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43861:15"/>the Lord, crying out from heaven to you, Weep not for us, but weep for your ſelves, who yet live in the Regions of Death, in the Borders of Sin and miſery. Why do ye parents forbid the Children to come unto Chriſt? Can ye believe the Mothers em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces ſofter than the Arms of their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? Are they not much happier in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brams</hi> Boſom, than in the Parents Lapp? If you have loſt a Child on earth, you have brought forth a Saint now in Heaven.<note place="margin">Ubertim fluentes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrimas reprime, ne grandis pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etas in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potem apud incredulas mentes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speratio put etur in Deum. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderandus eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibi, quaſi ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens, non quaſi mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus, &amp;c. — Illum expectare, non ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aris. [Her. Ep. <hi>24.</hi> ad Hebrid.]</note> Why do ye (ô Friends) put on Blacks for them, who have put on their white Robes? Why ſhed ye tears for them, whoſe tears are wip'd from their eyes? VVhy ſuch Groans and Lamentations for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe mouthes are filled with ſongs and praiſes, to him that ſitteth on the Throne, &amp; to the Lamb for ever and ever? This is not kindneſſe, but Envy, or ſome miſapprehenſion; or misbelief of their preſent condition. You grieve not thus for a Friend preferr'd to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Kingdom. <hi>Jacob</hi> turn'd his Tears into Joy, when he received his Son <hi>Joſeph</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43861:16"/>as from the dead; teſtor'd not to life only, but to a Throne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecondary Comfort from the ſtate irrevocable, unalterable, remedileſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>David</hi> rather chides and reproves (vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſtifling and ſuppreſſing his grief, as vain and unprofitable) than lenifieth or healeth it. Wherefore ſhould I now faſt? Can I bring him again? Can the conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of my fleſh reſtore his? Can my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer lend breath to the deceaſed? Can my howlings, like the Lioneſs, revive the young One? And if I beat my breaſt, is there any Hopes, that, as the Pelican by piercing her breaſt, I may reſtore to life? How can tears, that cannot make the ſtrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed flowers grow again, revive the interr'd Carkaſs? No hopes now; the Spirit is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to God that gave it, and no wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it out of his hands; The Plant dies in the ground, and yet through the ſcent of the water buds again; but Man dyeth and waſteth away, without hopes of ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, till the earth be no more, <hi>Jeh</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:43861:16"/>14, 8, 9, 10, &amp;c. Hee's gone, hee's gone paſt recall. No remedy. [VVe came not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, we muſt not go away together; what cannot be help d, muſt be endured. Theſe are the Common Cordials of vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Comforters. But what if your grief in the ſame Impatience with <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> ſhall reply, as he did to his Daughter <hi>Julia,</hi> thus comforting him (Sir, Your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints cannot recall, cannot help, but trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, all is paſt remedy) that is it which grieves chiefly, That there is no remedy, no cure of the wound, no Recovery of the Loſſe.</p>
            <p>Add then to theſe uncertain Comforts of Reaſon, which are as eaſily confuted by a more peeviſh and ſullen Reaſon, that is apt to diſpute for its paſsions,</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third comfort, from a Religious ſubmiſsion to God; For, as Reaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to yield to Neceſsity: So Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion bows us perfectly to ſtoop with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to this Neceſsity, as it proceeds from Gods Providence and Mercy, orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43861:17"/>even out Loſſes to our good. Here is that forcible Maſterer of our ſorrow to a neceſſary ſubmiſsion to the power of the Almighty, which we fooliſhly provoke while we reſiſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A voluntary Reſignation (ſhall I ſay to the Providence and mercifull diſpoſing) or even to the holy will of God, now manifeſtly declared by the event; for as his other will is revealed in his Word, to be the rule of our life and actions; ſo this Ordering; Governing, Over-ruling Will, <hi>revelata factis,</hi> diſcovers Gods ſecret pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, by the viſible effects, and iſſues of things, to be the rule of our paſſions and ſufferings. Do we dayly profeſs to God, <hi>Thy will be done,</hi> and now it appears to be particularly Gods will (ſeeing nothing is brought to paſſe in Heaven or in Earth without the will of him that ruleth over all) why doe we not give the Lord leave to do what he will in Heaven and Earth, whom we ſo often ſtanding profeſſe the Maker of Heaven and Earth? what Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43861:17"/>now poſſeſſeth us, becauſe Gods will croſseth ours, to ſtick at laſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce with good <hi>Eli</hi> (in as hard a caſe, as great a loſs as any we can complain of, the utter ruine of his family and Exciſion from the Prieſthood, the loſs of two ſons and the Ark of God at once) <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth good unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There is yet a greater reaſon of thy Reſignation in this Caſe; in that God hath the propriety and right, the Soveraign Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of all, we only the ſhort uſe. If God recall but his own Gift, what Injury, what ſo great cauſe of complaint? May not God as well take the Child away from the Mother, to whom it was committed only to breed up in the fear of God, as the Mother takes it home from the Nurſe? 'Tis call'd to a better home, what Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Title ſoever thou canſt plead in the dear loſs, Whether thy Husband, thy Child thy Father, Brother, or thy friend (which is as thy own ſoul) God pleads a nearer claim, his Creature, his Image, his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43861:18"/>the price of his redemption, &amp;c. his by many Titles, his even before he was, and his when he ſhall not be.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Duty or Inquiry, How we are from the preſent ſenſe of anothers death, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for our own.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Prepare by a tender and watchfull apprehenſion of all thoſe Memento's and Remembrances of Mortality, wherewith God and Nature dayly allarum us, ſo that nothing is more frequently repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, howſoever nothing be leſs thought on than death, and we at laſt complain of a ſurpriſal; Like to the Man in the old ſtory, who had covenanted with death, that he ſhould before his laſt ſtroak give ſome warning, with a Finger at leaſt lift up; and yet after many funerals of his friends, and many parcel-funerals, and decayes of his own body and ſenſes, being to die, required ſome other Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Fore-runners of his end, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged Death for not knocking at the door
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43861:18"/>before he entred, only becauſe he would not hear the knocks.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the many Remembrances of death,<note place="margin">So the Captain of fifty ſeeing the other Captains conſum'd by ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, foll upon his face, with I pray thee let my life be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in thy ſight, <hi>2</hi> Kings <hi>1 13.</hi>
               </note> the moſt ſenſible and ſharp admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions towards this preparation, are ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to us by the Laſt groans of our expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring friends, as by the laſt Trump, that Grave which buries part of our Souls with their bodies, muſt needs call ſome of our thoughts that way. And how few are there amongſt us that have lived half the age of man, that hath not out-lived half his Family or Acquaintance. That conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Felicity of the Grecian Prince, to paſs an whole age without the loſſs of one Friend, was a glory or boaſt not to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by many. Now the firſt prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for death, is the premeditation of it. Death, like the Baſilisk, loſing its ſting and force, being firſt ſeen and viewed by us.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Prepare, not only by a wearineſs and contempt of life, and of the world, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you no longer find your Friend, but by a more comfortable Thought of going to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43861:19"/>him, and over-taking him. Prepare to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. If this could ſo ſweeten <hi>Socrates</hi> laſt deadly draught, the Thought of paſsing to the ſociety of <hi>Orpheus, Homer,</hi> and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Sages, How much more ſhould it make us gladly embrace death, that leads us to the ſociety of Angels, and takes us not away, but reſtores us to our Friends, and to the Spirits of Juſt men, made perfect by the Viſion of the moſt Holy One? Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if we conſider, that the Friends we go away to, are much more than thoſe we part from. VVe are gatherd to our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Prepare, by caſting aſide all that makes Death bitter or terrible unto us. Now we fear death (ſaith the Monk, on <hi>Climacus</hi>) for one of theſe two Cauſes; either becauſe we love this preſent Life, or Diſtruſt a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. So <hi>Reuben, Gad,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſe,</hi> did chuſe their ſeat on this ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> becauſe they ſaw the ground fit for paſture, <hi>Num.</hi> 32 5. Some there are unwilling to leave their Paſtures, and Cattel, for all the beaſts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43861:19"/>and houſes Divines or Aſtrologers talk of in heaven. Some, with St <hi>Peter,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with the Glories, and bright Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the world, cry out in an Extaſie, <hi>It is good to be here, let's here fix our Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;</hi> but the Text tells us, He knew not what he ſaid, being dazled with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious light, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.33. Others, that with the Apoſtles betray a fear of ſtorms, and the danger of death, though Chriſt be in the ſtorm with them, deſerve Chriſts check, <hi>O ye of little faith, what are you afraid of?</hi> So that our whole work of Preparation is reduc'd to theſe two points,
<q>
                  <l>Contempt of this world,</l>
                  <l>Faith, hopes of a better.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>that we ſtrive to leave the world, its noiſe, and vanities, before we depart out of it. Look on the earth, and all his Comforts, as paſſengers in ſwift ſtreams, ſtill fleeting and parting from us, or we from it; and as Sojourners or Pilgrims abſtain from fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, never fix our delight in a pleaſant way, or Inne, which is ſuddenly to be quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43861:20"/>And ſeeing no diſtance can hinder us, more than the baniſh'd Jews, from tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our faces towards the heavenly <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> let us (that we may be able with the Martyrs of old, to refuſe Life, in hopes of a better Reſurrection) lay hold on Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, before this life fail us; lay hold by a lively faith on the hands of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſtretch'd out to receive us, and lay that ſure foundation for the time to come, of Good Works, that beſt preparative to a good death, a good life.</p>
            <p>Let us not reſt, till we have brought our Souls to that temper of the good Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, <hi>[Summan, nec metuas diem, nec optes,]</hi> neither to fear, nor deſire, over-paſsionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the day of our change, or rather to this Reſolution of St. <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>If I live, I ſhall do well; if I die, I ſhall do better. To me to live is Chriſt, To die is Gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now that we may with <hi>David</hi> riſe from our ſorrow, and waſh our faces with tears of Joy, in the thought of this Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43861:20"/>who is not loſt, but gone before us to that place, whither we all ſtrive to follow: Let us reflect on that principal Comfort, the hopes of that life, however loſt on earth to us, yet recover'd in heaven being hid with Chriſt. While your Eyes over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow with tears, being fixed on the Corps, on the Mantle here dropt below, ſend your thoughts beyond your ſight, after the better part, aſcended above to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, as we have great cauſe to believe and hope, by the aſſurances of eternal life in this Virgin departed? And what greater aſſurance can there be? <q>If (in the words of the Church) we are to know for a truth,<note place="margin">Preface be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Catechiſm.</note> and it is certain by Gods word, that Children being baptized have all things neceſſary for their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and are undoubtedly ſaved.</q> How much more this child? who was bleſſed with a <hi>Lois,</hi> and an <hi>Eunice,</hi> that gave her a Bible for the firſt thing to play withall, and taught her firſt to liſp the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> before ſhe could ſpeak her
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43861:21"/>Mothers Tongue, who even with her milk ſuck'd in the ſincerer milk of the word. As they write of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that at three years ſhe entred the Temple, offer'd her ſelf as a living Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice at the Altar; warm'd her hands and her heart at the holy flame, and made Religion her paſtime before the vanities of the world, or the pleaſures of ſin could ſeduce her; ſo was this Virgin brought by her Parents to the Temple (as it were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her Saviours ſteps) to ask of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors the way of life, even before ſhe could firmly walk in it. She learn'd Repentance ere ſhe knew what it was to Sin; She firſt began the life of Grace, ere ſhe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the full life of Nature, and had her Senſes exerciſed in the knowledge of Good and Evil, before ſhe could diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the degree of bravery and Pride. She yeelded her ſelf to be regulated by Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before ſhe could be abuſed by ſenſe or reaſon. Her firſt care was not her Dreſs, or Looks, but her <hi>penſum quotidianum de
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43861:21"/>flore Scripturarum</hi> (as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> directs, <hi>Laetal. l.</hi> 2. Ep.) her dayly task out of the choiceſt Scripture, to ſanctifie her memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as well as her Affections.</p>
            <p>Inſtead of wanton Songs ſhe repeated the Pſalms (which was an ability requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make a Divine in the Primitive times) but was it not ſtrange in thoſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der years? ſhe had not only ſtrength and force to hold <hi>Davids</hi> Harp, but to tune it: when others of her ſoft age would call for a Companion, ſhe cryed out, come Lord Jeſu, come quickly! and I pray thee help thy ſervant, whom thou haſt redeemed with thy moſt precious blood.</p>
            <p>What can we imagin, but that ſhe (who breath'd her firſt air in Devotion, and her laſt in Prayers, who was ſealed to eternal life by Baptiſme, and kept in the aſſurance and bleſſed hope thereof by a pious educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) had gained the Love of our Saviour, much ſooner than the young man, who had obſerved all that God commanded e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from his youth, though not ſo perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43861:22"/>as he conceived. In ſumme, ſhe was brought up One of the Order of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Virgins, who from her Infancy onely ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the things of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And here, might it be ſafe to expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with the Almighty, I ſhould aske, Why theſe Graces that are not to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in vain by us, or rather Offer'd than Given? Why ſo fair characters, that others might take copies from, thus immediately blotted out, and duſt thrown on them? VVhy doth God delight to crop ſuch fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant flowers in the bud, ere they are fully blown?</p>
            <p>Is it that the unwholſom Air, or rude Touch might not fully them? Indeed ſo we read ſome haſtily ſnatched out of the world, as out of a Peſt-houſe, <hi>Ne malitia corrumperet Intellectum,</hi> before Malice or Vanity ſhould infect their minds. Some are taken away out of a ſpecial Love and Tenderneſs of God; becauſe there is ſome good Thing in them towards the Lord God: as <hi>Jeroboams</hi> ſon, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.13. Is it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43861:22"/>to ſhew that we have here no abiding Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? that this world is but our Tyring room, or ſtage, where ſome Mute perſons are brought in onely for Number or ſhew, meerly to paſſe over the Stage, and ſo ſerve to grace it, even in the Paſſage, not unlike Angelical apparitions.</p>
            <p>Or is it (as a devout penſive VVriter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) that God trains us, as we do our children, by giving them gay and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, but demanding them immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately again, to try our Submiſsion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we could with <hi>Abram,</hi> yield up, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice a child at Gods call, and give thanks with <hi>Job</hi> to God, even when he reſumes his Gifts — <hi>(The Lord giveth, and the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away; Bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not this yet diſcourage Parents from making their Children fit for Heaven and the ſociety of Angels; But rather ſhame thoſe careleſs and indulgent Parents. (Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents indeed, as the Apoſtle terms them, afte rthe fleſh, as who had no ſhare in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43861:23"/>Soul) who being forward to ſurrender to God in Baptiſm, by a moſt holy Vow, the Children they received from him, are not yet afraid (with <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi>) to withdraw that they had once devoted to the Lord: and neglect the teaching them to keep their Vow, as religiouſly at leaſt as formal Nuns would. VVill they not allow that Diligence that ſenſeleſſe Creatures uſe in trayning and practiſing their young ones? ſeeing we bring them forth as deformed and miſhapen in the ſight of God, as any ugly Lumps of fleſh the Bear is ſaid to whelp; Shall we deny them the labour of our Tongues, to inſtruct them, and to lick them into ſhape? Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving betray'd them to a life of Sin and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, Ought we not in conſcience, in Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, procure them that other life of grace and glory? Let the Duty or the Shame, the Terror or the Comfort, anſwerable to the Education of your Children, move you to expreſs your Affection in this pious Care of providing a richer ſtock of manners,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43861:23"/>then of Fortunes, and hopes of a more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Inheritance. St. <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerves from <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 18.28. <hi>The Sonne ſhall not bear the iniquity of the Father, nor the Father the iniquity of the Son.</hi>—That this only frees and ſecures the Parents in theſe Children, that yet arrive not to the uſe of Reaſon, that live not on their own ſcore, that have no proper Motion of their own, but (as the Parents limbs) what the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents derive to them: in theſe the Parents negligence, or ſinfull Indulgence makes them (who are ſaid to live again in their Children) to periſh rather in their ſinfull courſes, and to invert the threat of the Commandement, that the ſins of the 3 and 4 Generation ſhall be viſited and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on the Parents, who have propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated thoſe ſins, by their looſe neglect or example: On the other ſide the joy of thoſe ſhall be redoubled and multiplyed with their ſeed, who being not more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious to enlarge their Family than the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43861:24"/>Houſhold of the Faithfull, or to propagate their own name more than Gods, may with boldneſs preſent themſelves with their righteous ſeed, at the Throne of God; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold us, and the Children that thou haſt given us. Theſe are they that may with more comfort loſe their Children at Gods Call, than others enjoy them amidſt other frail poſſeſsions, and uncertain contents of this life, ſeeing children ſo loſt, are not to be accounted loſt; Whence (the Father obſerves) <hi>Job</hi> having by his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence merited a double Reſtitution of all his other loſſes, had not his Children re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled, for they are not taken away, they are only ſecured in the hands of God, and ſent as pledges before us, to be more happily recovered and enjoyed for ever, when ſome ſhall be gathered to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and others more gloriouſly gather'd to their Children, whom they are to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, firſt in their Innocence, then in their Inheritance and Happineſs; That
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43861:24"/>Kingdom of Heaven which none ſhall enter that are not like unto thoſe little Children. To both which God fit us, and then haſten his Kingdom! Even ſo, ſweet Jeſu, come quickly. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
